Finding Aid for Christ Church (Detroit, Mich.: United Church of Christ) records, 1886-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Christ Church (Detroit, Mich.: United Church of Christ) records 1886-1966
Christ Church (Detroit, Mich.: United Church of Christ).
1 linear foot
9790 Ba 2
Church originally established as Christ Evangelical Lutheran Church, then later (date uncertain) as Christ Evangelical and Reformed Church. After 1961, the name became Christ Church, United Church of Christ. The church originally served the German community of Detroit. Church government documents; record books of marriages, baptisms, and funerals; and consistory minutes.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Christ Church through Mildred Bachmann (donor no. 8621 ) in July, 1997.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Christ Church was organized on the west side of Detroit in 1886, and was originally called Christ Evangelical Lutheran Church. This new congregation was formed by a group of people who split from the Lutheran Church at Ash and 23rd Street. After holding services in a Michigan Avenue store, the new congregation built a sanctuary located at the corner of Roosevelt and Myrtle. The first members of the church were ethnic Germans from East Prussia, and in fact records were kept in German until as late as 1926. Denominationally, Christ Church was maintained as a member of the Evangelical and Reform Church. In 1961, the Evangelical and Reform Church merged with the Congregational Church to form the United Church of Christ (UCC), and Christ Church became part of the UCC system. In 1977, Christ Church merged with a nearby UCC congregation, the Boulevard Church. The merged congregation was renamed Joy Church, and meets at the Boulevard sanctuary on Joy Road. The Church at Roosevelt and Myrtle was subsequently sold.
The records (most of which are in German prior to 1926) are arranged in three series: Church Government Documents, Record Books, and Consistory Minutes.
Subjects:
Christ Church (Detroit, Mich.: United Church of Christ); United Church of Christ--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; German Americans--Michigan--Detroit.
- Church Government Documents
  The Church Government Documents series contains documents relating to the governance of the church. These include the original articles of incorporation and several church constitutions.
  - Articles of Incorporation and List of Original Members, 1887 (Box 1)
  - Charter Members of 1896 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Church Constitution, 1944 (Box 1)
- Record Books
  The Record Books series consists of three record books which document marriages, baptisms, funerals and other church activities.
  - Marriages and Funerals, 1887-1894 (Box 1)
  - Baptisms, 1884-1894 (Box 1)
  - Pastors; Baptisms, 1894-1954; Lord's Supper; Memorial Gifts; Confirmation, 1926-1945; Funerals, 1895-1953; New Members, 1939-1953; Confirmation Classes, 1946-1953; Marriages, 1895-1953; Confirmation, 1895-1925 (Box 1)
- Consistory Minutes
  The Consistory Minutes series documents the meetings of Christ Church's consistory. The consistory is the body that governs the church, and its minutes document church finances and contain discussions of church activities.
  - 1887-1896 (Box 1)
  - 1896-1904 (Box 1)
  - 1904-1912 (Box 1)
  - 1912-1920 (Box 1)
  - 1920-1932 (Box 1)
  - 1933-1941 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1955-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1966 (Box 1)
- Other
  - Notebook of ministers, ca. 1976 (Box 1)